well it was obviously what we spoke
yesterday was in relation to the um
oh you know
be able to say something and
whether it's the suit as whether it's
personally personal to convey to the
others but that was in the reference of
you know running the monastery and
helping people and so on but
the same thing actually it's even more
useful for your own practice so even if it's
for your own practice so even if it's
not being
made for public directed to the public
being able to convey
to write down to explain to describe
what you think you understood will be
the measure of your understanding so
that's that's when you individual man don't
that's when you individual man don't
think you understood something unless
you can write it down and when somebody
says oh such-and-such claims the final
oh such-and-such claims the final
knowledge they say oh let's go and
question him
in other words let's go and see what he
has to say
because they themselves being our hands
with the final knowledge can tell what
he's describing whether it's accurate to
what extent it's accurate and so on
and adopting that as a principle
adopting that as a principle
to be able to convey to write it down to
explain it to others or something like
that uh it's it's actually good
uh it's it's actually good
because if you don't it's easy to slip
into that kind of
state of oh well i understood
what i need to understand or i am
practicing towards understanding i just
can't put it in words
i often heard that from people which
kind of results in
you know spending decades in robes and
not being able to formulate an
intelligible sentence when it comes to
tama without resorting to like you know
some mystical views or or just parroting
oh well this sergeant says this yeah but
what is your understanding of that
can you convey it can you explain it
and that also then brings to the that
second point of being able to
can you just speak about what you're
understanding how you're understanding
in front of others or is that already an
issue because if it's an issue then it
should be recognized as an issue like
what's why why do i fear if somebody disagrees
why why do i fear if somebody disagrees
with me again
another new will or something obviously
you just don't don't go around preaching
for no reason
but that's not what i'm talking about
i'm talking about that
um oh i don't want to say something
because like you know if other person
disapproves with it my mind will be
bothered or i might start regretting
what i said it's like well yeah that's
how irrational mind works that's how
doubt works
so are you not saying and not pushing
things in the direction of understanding
interrogation and investigation because
you're afraid you might look like a fool
to yourself later on
and if so then you realize no that's
if so then you realize no that's
actually not a valid reason to not do it
so you have to accept that
responsibility and that risk that yeah
your own mind might start turning
against you and
annoying you and doubting and so on but
the only reason it can do that is
because you're trying to
get away with it get away with lack of
clarity get away with taking the stand
get away with taking the stand
when it comes to your views and if you
are taking a stand when it comes to your
views then you will feel vulnerable to
the extent that your views are not clear
and that's the thing that will make you
practice that will make you clarify so it
so it
encourages responsibility
uh yeah but it also does come down to
the actual
doing it
i mean yeah there is a truth in yes i
don't feel
qualified to teach
but that does not disqualify you from
being able to convey in a non-teaching
manner what you understood how you
understood it and to what extent and
question it and interrogate it
and that's how you will be able to teach
properly because you will clarify things
for yourself and then teaching others
will be a side effect of that that's not
why you're doing this you're doing it
because that's how understanding is
gained so for example
so for example
an exercise
we can do now
now it's like something that yesterday i
came across
the buddha talks about those views that
self suffering is created by oneself
suffering is created by oneself
or suffering is created by another or
suffering is suffering is created by
both or suffering is created by naida
so the buddha said all four views are
wrong it's the contact i passer so pressure
it's the contact i passer so pressure
means suffering is there
dependently there isn't but it's
important but then you could rightly sort of
but then you could rightly sort of
ask so
would it be wouldn't it be more correct
to think that it's suffering is created
by you you know through your own
negligence ignorance craving and so on
so how should that be understood then
it's the wrong order the idea that
suffering is created by you by you yeah
so in what sense so imagine now i'm
a
complete outsider
i'm familiar with the suttas but i would
i read that it doesn't make sense so i
asked you the question you say it's the
wrong order so how shall i understand
the right order then
just in your own words whatever you
would say to some random person that
asks you that question
uh so if we look at what the phenomena
of you is
proceeded i mean i won't say this right
it won't this isn't how i know that yeah
that's the whole point yeah
i'm saying this in a very kind of
abstract way i would with somebody who's
new who's like then i would probably
just like talk in a very different way
but yeah the the this this phenomena of
you in inverted commerce is preceded by
um things which i have no control over
therefore i'm not
i'm not
yeah myself yeah in the nutshell that's
exactly so even like the craving
the ignorance and stuff that's not your
creation you're subjected to it
you're subjected to it
yes you're accepting it welcoming it
acting out of it
that's why you remain bound to the
results of craving yeah to the results
of ignorance but if you were to look at
yourself you don't create that
phenomenon it did not it does not originate from
it did not it does not originate from
you
uh and in the same sense as the suit
says suffering is dependently arisen
that's exactly what he first so
um
yeah practically speaking
practically speaking
like somebody who completely you know
doesn't have any
regard for the noble ones no recognition
there's no virtue
it's less wrong for them to think
you are responsible it's better so the
all of you know the wrong views are not
all equally wrong
they're wrong because yes fundamentally
they don't point to the right thing but
some of them are less wrong
and this would be one of the less wrong
views so yes
so yes
it's better to think that it's all
created by you because then you will
leave yourself no excuse but to try and
deal with it if you start dealing with
it rightly you get to understand then
that okay so to that extent it's not
created by me
and obviously the whole suit
on the base of the answer the buddha
gave it becomes obvious oh he's talking
that ultimate sense so it's like no no
presence of suffering is due to the
presence of craving or presence of
contact presence or pressure and yes that's not
presence or pressure and yes that's not
something you do
that's something you're subjected to
but being ignorant in regard to what
you're subjected subjectivity you assume
the ownership act and so on and then as
a result of that mistake already you get
to think you are the one who created
suffering so even your view of suffering
is the result of your um
ignorance in regard to that pressure
that is dependently
the nature of that pressure yeah yeah so
so then okay so now that's clear to me
so
how can then i trained train myself in
regard to that pressure but do i just
take any pressure or is there any like a
set of prerequisites i gotta meet in
order for that pressure to be do it
rightly or i just find things that
bother me and i do them what how do i go
about it
how would they train myself in regard to
that pressure so i don't suffer
the statement i gave before was that
this phenomenon of self is preceded by
things that are outside of my control
so we could look at
examples of those things
that could help you develop and
establish that understanding
um
so for example
how are you feeling right now
okay but
so does that mean i can just at any
point in my life
in my life
no matter what i'm getting up to
sit down and ask that question
yeah and go in the right direction
well it's it will be abstract
if why why would it be what do i need to
do so it's not abstract
yeah it would be abstract that's exactly
my point so how can i then do it without
it
remaining abstract
what is the i mean others if they have
ideas they can say well central strength
that you yeah yeah
and that's why it's not optional
that's what like even if people
think the dhamma
without sense restraint or virtue
they're not thinking they're done um and
that's that brings to that other point
of like um i think we mentioned that in
our recording when he was sitting with
us the other day it was like when people
think oh as long as i make any effort
towards the time in terms of thinking
pondering doesn't matter in what order
of things i do it
i'm on the path of the dumb because i'm
aiming towards liberation but it's like
well yeah abstractly you are sure
but it order of doing things matters and
saying what we said this morning like
you can have all the lofty ideas but if
you're not in doing things rightly on
the right level it's going to remain
abstraction that's kind of fueled by the
currently soothing and agreeable and
supportive circumstances
so so it's important because it's easy
to overlook
okay i understand that as i go by no no you
i understand that as i go by no no you
got to do that before and then the
pressure and everything else you feel on
account of that
will be on the right level where you can
just then endure it look at who you know
who's agree and all those contemplations
will have
more um room more more basis to apply
so that's why it's like whenever the
answer when everybody gave the answer to
the practice unless it was you know
somebody was already in the path but you
needed some specific clarification
that answer was always on the level of
uh gradual training
it just
it's not optional
and the order of developing that
training is the the way you have to do
it yes you can parallel to your you know
virtual center stream you can't keep
thinking about the diameter we say oh
you must stop thinking until you can do
it but don't put the emphasis on that
don't think that's the practice the
practice is actually upholding the
virtue destroying the senses and sort of
containing your otherwise uncontained mind
so that's just something i read this
morning and i'll give it to you
and i'll give it to you
not that i have the answer
so
the buddha says
that one should
regard pleasant feeling as pain
and painful feeling as a dart
and neutral well neither pleasant nor
painful feeling
has a nature
why
pleasure has pain
why must i become pleasant feeling
that i
enjoy why must i regard that as
why must i regard that as
painful
because it's pleasant
you know
what's painful about contradiction
yeah what is painful about it pleasure
as a really i mean yeah this is the
the abstract answer with an ignorant
mind one will automatically crave more
pleasure when one experiences
pleasure um
um
so if there's an ice cream the thought
of the ice cream
is pleasant
and the reason why it's pleasant is
because there is
it's contained within
this underlying
lack of an ice cream this pain this
uneasiness that makes that ice cream
that phenomena pleasurable
so if one were to
with ignorance one might think are the
pleasure is in the ice cream or there there is um
is in the ice cream or there there is um
yeah so one is in that sense perceiving
feeling but actually if i wanted to feel
but actually if i wanted to feel
the feeling in that
scenario it would be
painful because there would be a sense
of
wanting more of the pleasure
so it's only it's only pleasurable
because one lacks
context and relating regard to that that
feeling so like you have an idea of
so like you have an idea of
like the pleasure
[Music] but the
but the
the experience of it
you have the idea of like pleasure is
nice to have
but the experience of it is yeah
pain but now somebody says oh i'm aware of
but now somebody says oh i'm aware of
all that
but i'm just having the ice cream
nonetheless i'm just aware of all that
so what's the problem with that
well this is the question well i think
the problem if you say
i know that
well the problem is that you
are not
that's an abstract
theory like i know that pleasure is
not to be
sought after or pleasure is painful
but you're not acting like that you are
you are acting as though it is pleasant
so your idea you're saying one thing
you're doing the other thing and you're
doing this so this is what you actually
believe you believe that
you believe that
by places
that somebody is known as what yeah yeah
no matter what they're saying what are
they doing that's their belief that's
the way and uh so but so like for
example if somebody was again an
outsider so maybe they just now start to wander
so maybe they just now start to wander
even further and say okay but why is
the pleasure a problem
why do i need to free myself from
such a harmless pleasure like eating ice
cream for example
doesn't harm anyone uh
why do i need to regard that as pain so
to free my mind from it where i don't
see a problem with it where is the
problem what is the issue with
with allowing such pleasures
loss of perspective that is
in there
um
well this understanding that
of the nature of craving
leads to this this establishment whereby the
to this this establishment whereby the
mind is
isn't moved by
yeah more particular phenomena or it's
able to become establishing
so in other words it's a it's a weakness
you give into and the more you give in
to the weaker you become
yeah by acting out of it then exactly
you keep yourself dependable and acting
out of it yeah so yeah
that's the whole point
so the pleasure of having an ice cream
is
it's not
exactly a wholesome thing in
you know people don't regard it as
something very unusual but it's is it
necessary to do well that's the thing
you know it's not an wholesome ice cream
it's not a wholesome your desire behind
is what's unwholesome
so if you judge your desire by the
object of your desire then you won't
necessarily see a problem because
sometimes there is no problem in the
object of the desire
and that's but see unknowingly then you
actually perpetuate the problem which is
the desire so if you can eat the ice
cream desirelessly as the buddha said
the only blame
blameless person it's not what you eat
it's not if you're vegan or vegetarian
or whatever else or you told it stuff
they've fallen from a tree the only
blameless one is the one that eats
without a desire whatever you eat
so but not seeing that problem then
through eating something like an ice
cream which in itself is not an issue
you are carrying the issue which sooner
or later then it's going to bite you
back
the desire will come that's what was
that suffering is not getting what you
want and the problem of that is not things
and the problem of that is not things
that don't come to you the problem is
that you want them in the first place
which means sooner or later something
will not come your way because you want
it if you didn't want it well that comes
and goes makes no difference to you
so that's why even the slightest desire
with sensuality and central craving is
the problem
because the
the the root of suffering the root of
dependence is that desire not ice cream
or this or that not pleasure not pain in
a way yeah well it's it's avoiding pain
sure um but so the the pleasure you get on
um but so the the pleasure you get on
account of
the object of desire you engage with is
secondary to the basically pain of the desire
to the basically pain of the desire
you're trying to avoid by doing it
that's where the issue is
but is it possible to eat without desire
yes
with what intention to sustain the body
to whatever yeah he feels hunger in his
belly he puts stuff in it yeah but isn't
that also in some way desire
no to sustain the body to live long no
that's just an intention
so arahant can have intentions without a
desire that's the difference there but yes if
that's the difference there but yes if
you can see the difference you'll be at
least a certified
mm-hmm so actually how can you have how
can you have intention without a desire
but i can intend without desire but he does
i can intend without desire but he does
not recognize it exactly yeah that is
possible
well again we're not talking about the
abstract platoons what they might do
we're talking about a personal point of
view which is either putujina or on the
way to be another hand or what intention
is so i can abstractly theoretically yes
puttugena can do that but that doesn't
mean that akutujana should start
thinking now oh i am doing that no no no
no
well i know you're not implying that but
the way you talk about it implies that
right so if somebody else hears that ah
super tuchen i can't then eat without a
desire oh yeah i do that sometimes no
you don't
the only way to do it
is to know it's to know that you're not
doing it yes but so the problem is not
seeing the what nionovira says that intention
the what nionovira says that intention
does not necessarily imply craving yes
exactly yeah
that needs to be seen that needs to be
thoroughly understood
and that's why it only the dhamma and
even talking about animals should only
be done on that personal level because
it's already misunderstood and it's much
easier to misunderstand if i make a
again theoretically correct statement that yes
theoretically correct statement that yes
a petuna can
intend without desire
accidentally exactly but see
from his point of view he can't because
all he sees is the desire so an arahant
can see that sometimes you do it without
desire but that doesn't his point of
view does not apply to you
so that's why you need to like make some
special care to not talk in such in
personal senses because people already
are way too keen to assume they're
already on the path simply by thinking
the dharma they're already towards our
hanship by being inspired and so on
by being inspired and so on
and and that's why yeah from the
personal point of view that's where the
problem is and that's what the solution
is so if you start thinking okay
everything i do is rooted in desire
how they free myself from it
so although it's
there are some instances you're not
rooting desire
by saying that everything is rooted in
desire will kind of force you to be very
very careful and look until you do
discern and then you can relax sure but
if you try to relax sooner it's going to
end up masking some problem or the other
oh well if you try to relax sooner
you'll be rooted in desire
but i've been now answered why these
sensual pleasures are painful
because that was the oh oh right now
yeah why why is pleasure
painful of our life to be seen as
painful yeah why should it be seen
because because that's the instruction
you should be regardless as such so
something is fashionable but now
somebody says you should see it as
painful but
but
the more one understands why that
instruction is valid the better one will
be able to regard it as such
well you could take it on faith but it
would be a bit of a clash like okay i
experienced pleasure but i should not
then i feel guilty or something but
well now we're going to talk about
petunia again but like he he does not
see an escape from suffering so the only
way he can deal with that is his painful
it's destruction just put the essential
pleasures over against it yeah but now
somebody who does see these four noble
truths right
the origin and by suffering ceases
doesn't depend on sensual pleasures in
order to allow the suffering to cease
because he's got this third noble truth
which is which is cessation of suffering
so
and and so that's exactly the answer
there why why do you need to do that yes
and so then
seeing where suffering ceases
this whole this whole domain of
sensuality stands out as quiet
superfluous it's not necessary anymore
to put that over against pain
but that might still be the spool
due to how much
how prone somebody wants to sense your
pleasures but they are not necessary
anymore to deal with this whole burden
of existence so so is that why then
you should regard
prospect of pleasure as painful well
this would be my answer yes because it
does so does that mean that this should
uh would refer only to somebody with the
right view
which is that the one that that at least
well yeah well that that's what makes
precisely the distinction it's as an
ordinary person
it has no other way of dealing with a
risen suffering other than putting
central pleasures up against it but now
here somebody who sees the dhamma has
another way
and so this is why it should be seen as
painful because these things well my
understanding is that essential places
sit on top of the pain
for ordinary person and so he first to
learn to not go in that direction which
will make the pain more salient but
that's precisely how you can
well that's my pose how one can then
discern the origin of that pain
if that's not gonna be the prominent
thing which takes out it's gonna be
difficult to see how it originates
so can can then
an outsider then just start applying
attitude of every pain will be every
pleasure will be regarded as painful
well yes
if
if he sees every sensual pleasure as
painful whenever he is
whenever he is
desire for essential pleasure if he
remembers that that is going against the
dharma and will prevent him from seeing
the actual origin of suffering
if no he does i mean an outsider
doesn't see the origin of suffering yeah
would he benefit from simply what he
said first uh
attitude should be developed whereby
should be developed whereby
uh pleasure is seen as pain
well i would say as
as
a
upon the pain so there is something that
sits sort of below it and that is that
is where you want to go so don't go in
the direction of the sense of pleasure
but go into the direction of the pain
that is that is below it
and if you see that that sense your
pleasure is your attitude of dealing
with that pain
seeing that it depends on it then that
which depends on pain is part of the
pain and so you consider the guy that is
painful right
right
but and yeah that would be the result if
you understand things yeah what you're
saying is somebody who doesn't
understand well would could they understand if they
well would could they understand if they
just regard
uh pleasure is painful would they have
an understanding you just described well
if somebody has faith they might but if
they incline towards understanding they
might not work on understanding sir well
if if somebody has faith in the buddhist
instruction they might just take that as
a valid teaching and start regarding
things like that
and and that might have results
but it's also possible that somebody
wants to work on the understanding first
and but arrive
sure sure sure no just yeah yeah so
so what would happen to somebody
who is not familiar with the buddhist
is not familiar with the buddhist
teaching but for some reason adopts that
attitude yeah that's every pleasure is painful
yeah that's every pleasure is painful
yeah and because of that attitude he
doesn't engage with that pleasure
how far can he take
well he that
be able to properly restrain himself in
sense or pleasures
what does it mean properly strength like
free himself from sensuality it's just
it's just
well yeah if
if yeah
yeah if some ordinary person goes to the
buddha he is just his teaching and has
faith he might be able to abandon you
without even without a buddha if an
ordinary outsider
would adopt this attitude that every
pleasure is actually painful and and
sustain that attitude for the duration
of the pleasure pull of the pleasure
that he endures he would be able to free
himself from the assumption of
sensuality and that's why the buddha did say like
and that's why the buddha did say like
outside of this dispensation there are
someone as ibrahims that have uprooted
yes uh essential desires completely
rightly not not wrongly
um because so if you are you your
attitude you develop this attitude of
pleasure but pleasure itself is painful
but pleasure itself is painful
our sense of pleasure because there's
also unbroadly pleasure which is
unbroadly pleasure which is
which is the whole place but yeah which
can only be discerned after you have
thoroughly withdrawn yourself from the
central pledge exactly right so that's
not something that you can so you said
unworldly pleasure the pleasure of
renunciation yeah i was referring to john
yeah i was referring to john
yeah
but yeah
pleasure of enunciation arises pleasure as pleasure as
painful
but you don't know why
why is it painful yeah well you might
know you might have an inkling you might
not know you might just make it just
some people might do it dispassionate
with it
if you if you regard it like that long
enough yeah why why would that happen
though why if you regard it long enough as
why if you regard it long enough as
painful
why would then you at one point
see through it and become free from it
because it is exactly that's exactly why
because it is factually painful and
violent so you don't know the reason or
you're not entirely clear on your
reasons why you're regarding it as
painful you stick to that attitude out
of faith out of intellectual pondering
out of something
and because it factually is so you get
to see it because you are actually
emulating what it actually is
and then oh the danger did become
apparent in the lack of satisfaction and
then you there is no more desire towards
it in the same sense there is no more
desire towards the food that you just
vomited
when you recognize it for what it is
so the second
says and then regard pain for feeling as
a dart
because if you are experiencing pleasure and
if you are experiencing pleasure and
regarding that as pain
and you're stepping away from that then
when you get pain
that's even more unwanted
and that's more like well actually no i
don't answer maybe somebody else can
answer it why okay let's move to the
next one so then
why would then
what would be the benefit of regarding
pain as a deadly diet
well then it reinforces that uh
disenchantment that detachment from
feeling
yeah yeah because what
sure but this kind of refers to you know you
but this kind of refers to you know you
have pleasure pull of pleasure then you
have the pull of pain
as in the pressure of pain
so why would that be then what would be
the benefit of regarding the pressure of
pain or regard that as a deadly arrow
in the same sense we discovered the
practical benefit of regarding pleasure
as painful i it emulates what it
actually is so sooner or later if you
stick to it you will be uploading the
desire towards it because you're seeing
it as not pleasant anymore
so what is it that you would see
if you are
regarding pain as a dead hero
that pain can come to you regardless
whether you want it or not
right so that you're entirely enclosed
and liable to it it just strikes you and
how's that felt then
so if you are at any given second at
risk of being struck by a deadly error
yes uh could you become careless
could you get easily distracted
could you forget about the practice and
like postpone it no it would just keep
you on your toes
effortlessly all you need to do is protect that
all you need to do is protect that
context and you're effortlessly mindful
and careful and watchful
so yeah if you develop that attitude
then you don't have to focus on
pulling all these other neglected
aspects and so on of practice because
everything will be amplified
but now obviously that does not mean
that when there is neither pleasure
nor pain
you keep trying to get the sense of pain
and urgency
because the third one is when there is
neither pleasure nor pain you
contemplate that uh changeability
impermanence on each other
so at any moment it can become either
pleasure so it's not felt there it's
just neutral feeling
so when things are neither pleasant or
unpleasant that's what you look at that
on each aspect of it
and what's the benefit of that
practical benefit of looking at nature
when it's not pleasant
can relax for a sense of urgency yeah
but why why can't you just look at the
nature when pleasure is pleasant or when
pain is present why shouldn't you look
at the picture then
sorry because it's usually rooted in a
treat yeah because you'll be doing it for the
yeah because you'll be doing it for the
wrong reasons
so when it's
when you're not pulled by pleasure or
pressured by pain
then ah you can now do the amnesia because
ah you can now do the amnesia because
you won't be rooted in trying to get rid
of anything
yeah i think it also says somewhere that
then neither pleasure nor pain
is
not seen not in this uh not seen it's
felt as unpleasant felt unpleasantly
when it's seen it's felt pleasantly yeah
but that's without the level of that
high pleasure yes yes
because if you if you were to practice
that seeing pleasure as painful and pain as
seeing pleasure as painful and pain as
dark
mindful not trying to get rid of the pain not
not trying to get rid of the pain not
trying to get more pleasure
and you're kind of developing that
i would say the outcome is
neutral experience neutral feeling experience
experience neutral feeling experience
feeling of peace
when it's known
when it becomes known yeah that becomes
your no no
to you
yeah but
you must now regard that
experience that feeling as a nietzsche
again not something that you
must delight in
or distract yourself from or or keep it
on the level of uh
being unclear yeah that's why neutral
feeling when not known
is felt unpleasantly so you know so
what also is going to happen is that if
you actually are sense restraint virtues
uh
not going towards sensuality not trying
to get rid of the pain out of the habit
then you realize it's going to what's
going to happen is that then
something seemingly painful that you're
experiencing within that setup you'll
realize oh this is painful only because
i'm not looking at it
or this is suffering because i'm yeah
it's suffering because i'm ignoring it
so you realize that
within that setup you're actually going
to have many neutral feelings that would
be bothering you
simply because you're looking elsewhere
and that's that neutral feeling needs to
be known and once you start to recognize
and you're like oh yeah so the this i
still assume this is the pain of the
desires that it wasn't actually
the pain of the desire stopped when i
stopped engaging with desires
now this is the pain of the like lack of
clarity in regard to this and similar
and that's that's also when it becomes
clearer that whole thing of like
replacing the
pain of sensuality
with the pain of renunciation because
it's a better pain
like the pain of a household life
replacing with the pain of the of their
enhanced lives
and then replace the pleasures of the
life with the pleasures of renunciation
so if your genuine experience is one of
mutual feelings
which is felt like uncertain
if that's what you look at it yeah if
that's what you look for
that yeah
like you i mean yes it's felt uncertain
for somebody that knows already where to
look for the nature yeah
but it will not uncertainty in itself it
will not be felt uncertain to somebody
who doesn't look for on each other
that's why it's encouraged to develop
the attitude of a nature towards that
because yes it's the purest example of
uncertainty that's neither pulling and
pressuring you
so it's the best basis to develop the
direct insight
but only if it's not done in response to
sensuality trying to get rid of it or
pain trying to act out of it
now somebody can get complacent when
there's a lot of this neither pleasant
not painful feeling
you might almost take a refuge in that
considering this is neither painful more
pleasant i.e it's quite agreeable
waiting to see that at any moment well
then when you're stuck with the other if
you're dishonest it's agreeable it's not
because if you if you even if you're
complacent if you simply look at it for
what it is
unless you're seeing amnesia it's going
to be felt unpleasant
so not known a neutral feeling is
actually felt painfully uh-huh yes
right so it's how you look at it determines
so it's how you look at it determines
how you're going to feel it let's say
like that yeah yeah yeah
painful because that which is
impermanent is suffering
no painful because you're ignoring the
that which is impermanent is suffering
if you don't ignore it anisha is very
pleasant recognizing it it's very
liberating and uplifting and
you know relieving you of all the burden
from the entire samsara
but when it's not seen for that then yes
then it's painful
to
when a nature is seen
not seen
it's painful yeah
but when it is known
if it's known that's how you free
yourself from that pain yeah
that's right through contemplating a
niche and dukkha you actually mind
becomes liberated
[Music]
uh so can you then contemplate anata
how do you contemplate another
or can you contemplate or not
what do you think
um well it's an
extension of venetian dukkha so the um
so okay let's say that i want to
contemplate or not i'm an outsider i
just come here i heard about nata it
makes sense to me i want to do the
practice of anata
what do i do
well how do i go about it in the right
way phenomena of self again
phenomena of self again
is preceded by
these these things which have arisen by
themselves which are a nature yeah
but i'm not asking what
i'm not asking what
an artist is i'm just asking how what
would you you know see
uh well
in regards to what we've just been
talking about to contemplate
nietzsche um
and see
thereby the the suffering of um
of
pleasant feelings and unpleasant
feelings and so can i just start with that what
and so can i just start with that what
are there any prerequisites that i have
to develop beforehand yeah central
strength and virtue yeah so you've got
to say that yeah you're gonna i'm an
outsider who comes and asks you about
anata and i know they are they
i'll just give you the answer but that
won't be the dumber for them yeah
so yes yeah you can contemplate an atta
by
developing uh
uh
taking on virtue
sense restraint guarding of the sense
dose the pain within that that arises
the pain within that that arises
then either don't resist it don't try to
get rid of it don't give in to the pain
of sensuality towards the desires
then you will be left with what's felt
within that setup and there you are
you're actually already doing the anata
whether you even think about terms of an
art or not that is what the native
practice of anatomy is
in the buddha the same he would always
give the entire spiel of the gradual
training because that is the answer
and i remember the first time i i read
the suit and somebody comes enough to
suffering and stuff and then he would
say yes i'll teach you the way
to to that exactly specific
acute question you post about how to
free myself from suffering and then he
starts giving the answer to that by
saying here a young man shaves off his hair
here a young man shaves off his hair
leaves the uh
household life restrain yourself with
the rules of fatima and i always thought
in the beginning okay yeah fine but come
on just
now give me the answer all of this is
obvious but no that is the answer every
single time
that needs to be done to arrive at the
answer if you think you can access the
answer without having met these
training of the right order
it won't be the answer you're getting
and people don't realize how important
that is
so how do i go about contemplating anata
well by keeping the precepts dwelling
the sense restraint watchful guarding of
the sense those
then the suffering you start
experiencing within that type of
container that has potential to be seen as a
that has potential to be seen as a
nature felt is due correctly and then
experience the whole experience as an
author if you don't do that
if you don't do that
setup
whatever you feel won't be what you
think you're feeling and that's like as
he would have said in maybe
someone no another
whatever he conceives to jinnah it's
always different than that
even if he's conceiving the dhamma or
whatever else it's always going to be
different than that
yes and there's also the assembly of
this uh
separate piece of wood you know there's
three similes
yeah and then it does say that that even
if he is experiencing painful vacant
feelings due to striving yep he's not
gonna get the results yeah because he's
never drawn exactly so then you know if
somebody does some we tweet somewhere
and has aching knees and aching back and
making a head and shoulder and stuff
like this on the counter sitting for 10
hours a day but they're not observing
any precepts then
then one might assume that there's a
sense of discipline involved in that but
but as you would say this on the wrong
level so there you go but now actually
to play devil's advocate but they are
observing the precepts during their
retreat yes but where's the problem so
what you said is correct exactly all the
pain they're going through
it's not going to result in the
knowledge no
although at the same time when they're
going through the pain they are keeping
the presets
well yes but why wouldn't result then in
the knowledge well because well actually
well actually
well okay so you are saying if they do
observe the precepts during that retweet
well if somebody has been observing the
precepts beforehand and has been
restrained beforehand then it's not
impossible that in fact they get results
on that retweet
but what i was trying to say is that
ordinarily people do not do that in let's say
people do not do that in let's say
household life and then they come to a
retreat most of the time there is not much
most of the time there is not much
emphasis on the virtue either so there
is sir so so the idea is then that okay
you cannot be bothered because this is
all like you know
this is all discipline narrow small
manner and so on so the discipline then
is not in uh on the level of sila but
the discipline is only conforming to a
schedule which tells you when to say
them to walk and all the ass of it so
basically their precepts are conditional
due to the circumstances circumstances
are making them keep the precepts
yeah that's exactly why right
yeah right no no even if they keep the
perfect precept if it's rooted in
circumstances not their decision to put
the precepts and responsibility for the
intention behind the action first that's
why sharp racking pains painful feeling
will not result in the knowledge even if
they came to precepts before even either
keep the precepts after their retreat
even they keep doing the retreat the
view puts the precept second
if you assume the precept as a
conditional duty so i get this direct
access to what i'm trying to get
and that's why always that's why always
those retreats that are always based on
that are wrong because of that
because people arrive at it thinking
they are directly going for something
while what they should put first is
actually conditionally second yeah and
same goes for the monks by the way
somebody can be in rose for 50 years
pure virtue and still be a petuna
and that's exactly what's ill about the
paramount doing it conditionally on the level of
doing it conditionally on the level of
the sense of duty and that extent i'm
not putting it first as your practice
because if you do then you get the
weight of your intention
because now
it doesn't matter if the rule doesn't
specify i i i can or cannot do this
i know that it's rooted in the intention
affected with desire thus i won't do it
but see if i assume the precepts 200 and
570 of them doesn't matter but i assume
them as the external definitions then
anything not defined i can do and i
don't have to think about it
yeah and there is no practice for you at
all and that's unfortunately what's
and that's unfortunately what's
considered purity today in like
monasteries and temples it's the idea of
being overly defined about every little
aspect and sticking to it
and sticking to it
which automatically results in okay
putting your intention second
because the letter is important the
authority is important the tradition is
important the external definition is
important so even if you spend your lifetime doing
so even if you spend your lifetime doing
it
the and enduring lots of pain on account
of it there will be no wisdom arising on
a kind of sharp and painful feeling that
you're going through
because you're still keeping the
perversion in your core what comes first
yeah if shark breaking feelings arise at
all somebody could also just fall asleep
within that context sure sure
in a sense pleasurable that's the one
kind of
but then if you realize that that's what
comes first
putting the virtue so to reveal your
intentions for which you are already
assuming responsibility
then the idea of going on a retreat or
not well it's it's circumstantial like i
might go on a 10-day retreat just to
change the environment either way
internally my practice remains the same
exactly yes
not giving it to greed exactly exactly
there's no difference
there is no difference whether i'm here
or there my work is the same virtue
comes first intentions revealed on
account of my sense restraint is my work
so yes if i can have a time to you know
spend in in some quiet environment i'll
do that
because it's obviously
uh going to be like less harassing me
than if i stay in the middle of the city
but either way i gotta do i can't do the
practice only when i'm that's not the
practice that's just reacting
uh basically as a so like out of a
version towards the busy city
so i'm just trying to get rid of
discomfort by doing a retreat or
whatever else yeah
yeah
and now we're just you know we're still
we're talking just on the level of the
pure environment of retreat we're not
getting even into the what views are
being taught on the retreat that's
that's the issue itself yeah that's
gonna be another thing
now when you say that is that it's
important to put the intentions first
always in the context of the sila yeah
and to feel the weight and the burden of
that um can we connect that with the right
um can we connect that with the right
practice of mind monster breathing which
is also an exercise of putting intention
first or is that a bit of a leap how how would
or is that a bit of a leap how how would
you go about it
how would you connect it well tell me
more if i sit down and i'm breathing in
and i'm breathing out and i know that
i'm breathing in and breathing out then
that seems to me to be uh that that
that's a body act of body intention
breathing and breathing out it's
something that i'm doing all right so
referring that just a
general sense of what would be the right
application of anapanasati exactly oh
yeah definitely and i was trying to
connect that with the idea because this
seems to be one of the more popular
discourses because there's this tendency
to these methods and techniques and so
on yeah but once we have established
then it's not a method it's not a
technique yes and you see that that the
right virtue as we have just said is
about putting the intentions first then
then i was
trying to find out if if somebody has
understood all of that and they sit in
that retweet context and then somebody
rightly expounds anapanasati would that
not be seeing on a deeper level
that there are intentions going on and
that the whole practice is to see but it
won't it probably wouldn't happen
in the retreat setting it will happen in
solitude you don't go sit in a room full of
you don't go sit in a room full of
people to watch your breath that's
already effective yeah of course so if
somebody would have seen and developed
virtually rightly and already has the
right view
all he will need to do is have an empty
room yes so that's the extent close the door
yes so that's the extent close the door
that's the extent of solitude needed
and then then yes exactly then the
practice would be knowingly he breathes
in knowingly breathe out no will
everything yes so the no that's and it's
very much on the level of the intentions
and then knowingly i'll intend to
breathe like this knowingly i'll bleed
out like that knowingly i'll basically
while i'm breathing in i shall intend to
uh
relinquish things ideas
things ideas
activities that my mind holds
and that's the practice yeah it's the
practice of discerning the neutral
intention but to practice discerning the neutral
but to practice discerning the neutral
intention while you don't even see
wholesome and wholesome intention
while your virtue is defined by
circumstances and externally assume the
rules it does not apply to you yes
that's right anapanasati was told to
those who were at least thought upon us
and still had work to do
and there was another one i mentioned
that in that talk
um
when uh when the buddha says
you know much benefit to those who do it
do monks do it and vanderbilt says yes
lord i do want to punish
i do want to punish
and he says how did you do it he said
knowing i breathe in knowingly breathe
out and because of it i have before
before he says that huh i have abandoned
essential desires for past essential
pleasures future uh essential political future
future uh essential political future
sense of pleasure yeah i
um
well and free from them here and now
yeah he abandons those desires for
pleasures of the past and future and he
what's the word calms down in regards to
any resistance that is felt now oh yeah
resistance that is felt now oh yeah
yeah the internal resistance
he's abandoned there's so essential
pleasures what do you feel right
what do you feel right
he's the pain of existence yeah and then
he relaxes in regard to that
mindfully i breathe in mindfulness
yeah and then the buddha
because there is obviously the subtler
aspects of conceit and appropriation
left there
but you realize so first of all
wouldn't have been applying to him if he
wasn't at least the sotapanna
second of all
he was already he
freed himself from sensuality but seeing
the danger and so on and obviously
knowingly breathing in no english
breathing out he calmed down the fatigue
of the resistance to your own existence
which then uprooted that
tendency towards sensuality
and uh so in itself that's all you need
to do knowingly breathing or breathe out
that's iran
and when then you become free from
sensuality establishing the right view
then the rest of the anapanasati can
apply to you
so if somebody comes along here or
somewhere else and says one day can you
instruct me
you say yes
and then you start teaching the tell
them that they have to spend years of
developing virtue and that will be there
yeah so uh this puzzle by it you say
well the anapanasati you know uh
famously expounded indianapolis
yes was told by the buddha to those who
were at least sort of or higher yes so
until you reach that this does not apply
to you but can they sit down normally
you think normally without no
they cannot you would say
no definitely they cannot no with the
right context no no they won't be the
enemy that would be meditation with
sexuality yeah of course that would be
premeditating under meditating over
meditating meditating they will be
waiting waiting waiting for that to
happen no no because you don't see intentions
no no because you don't see intentions
how can you do on a panasonic rightly
when you haven't been sufficiently
cultivating the recognition of
intentions behind your actions where
wholesome and unwholesome is rooted
but any other panasonic by the
father's stretch of imagination
doesn't matter but still it will be
rooted in
sensuality trying to get the pleasure
trying to avoid the pain trying to avoid
responsibility trying to avoid dealing
with things that need to be dealt with
beforehand it will be give me this so i don't have
it will be give me this so i don't have
to actually do the work
give me the practice so i don't have to
practice so yeah why do you want to
practice on a panasonic
what's the reason because you do you
want some
something from it do you want some
future pleasure do you desire some future
pleasure do you desire some future
pleasure i
i want to okay let's let's play this
advocate again so well no
i want to break tana pansati
because uh it calms me down
and calmness is good so what's the
problem then what's the problem with me
doing on a panasonic if it calms me down
anybody could say
didn't say before
the teaching of the anakin society that
you abandoned
um
future well yeah i'll do that later but
well yeah i'll do that later but
factually
when i said
i'm not shotabana i don't know the
buddhist teaching that much but i went
on a retreat and i was taught under
penance when i sit and do it it calms me down
when i sit and do it it calms me down
factually what is wrong with that
nothing why is that a problem
well so that means i can do on the panasonic
so that means i can do on the panasonic
yeah unless you and as long as you don't
regard that to be what the buddha is
talking about so then it's not going to
panic but it is the buddhism
that i've been taught and i'm doing
yeah so there were so there is so the
day so it's either nodding
yeah so somebody might only assume that
they are practicing rightly and are
making progress that's the danger yeah
what else is the more acute danger
let's say that let's put on a problem
let's put underpants out to your side
what is the danger of me
valuing my kindness because your your it's
my kindness because your your it's
sensuality it's like uh yeah you're it's
it's not saying the pleasure was painful
yeah it's what else
sorry it's denying in a sense um
disturbance or trying to deal with it
or trying to deal with it
dealing with exactly it's it's
management as a conditional yes
so you're calm
when you get so it's like okay so you
value calmness which means you're not
uprooting the disturbance
like yes
you know it's nice to be calm but the
real question you should but why am i
disturbed in the first place
that's the problem but if i just do on a
panasonic for the calmness that i took
at face value as something that is
always good
means i'm taking simultaneously for the
face value that i will keep getting
disturbed so am i liable to future disturbance
so am i liable to future disturbance
once i calm myself yeah oh that's the
problem not that you were disturbed or
calm the problem is that you can get
disturbed and it always ties in with the view that
and it always ties in with the view that
see by valuing this calmness per se
means i don't kind of
what means all the views that i have
on account of what is the disturbing
aspect from for me will remain unchanged
because as long as i have access to the
technique of calmness that's how i deal
with it
but did the disturbance
did the disturbance
come from you not watching your nostrils
sufficiently enough is that how
disturbance entered you
so when you calm down how does that
disturbance come back why do you lose
that kindness
and then we're back onto our intentions
behind the actions
you cannot become disturbed accidentally
it cannot just happen to you you always
open the door for disturbance how
acting out of greed aversion delusion
that's it no other gateway
for disturbance to enter you
so all your efforts that are focused and
revolve around calming yourself are the
efforts of just plastering over a wound
that remains unchanged
and it always ties in with the views
that disturbance comes from the world
well it's the busy life it's the
business none of that i mean the robbers
chopping off your limbs should not be
disturbing you if you did the damage
rightly yeah
so through your practice of calmness
taken at face value you are maintaining
your wrong views of where the
disturbance actually is
so you only you the only way to force
yourself to deal with the disturbance
rightly then
is to not give in to the temptation to
manage it
through kindness
so
it's never good to do it
unless you have the right view you'll be
closer to counting yourself rightly
by pondering on the qualities of the
buddha the dhamma the sangha the sense
restraint the virtue taking
responsibility for your erection and
being watchful and careful before you do
things by body speech and mind that will
result in the factual samadhi i being
less likely less liable to be disturbed
even amidst the disturbances
and funny enough that's what the buddha
says in the sutras yes if you're not a
satyabana what your samadhi is it's like
recollecting the buddha the dhamma the
sangha the virtue
will unify your mind and basically uh
unify your mind and basically uh
make it unmovable in the face of things
they want to move it
yeah and the anniversary and the deities
exactly sometimes it says yeah so
develop those contexts actively
obviously with the virtue to match it
and and that that would be the factual
samadhi that would be the factual peace
and calmness that's not rooted in just
trying to manage a payment
and also it will not be fueling your
wrong view further of where the pain and
disturbance comes from in the first
place and this is why people keep coming back
and this is why people keep coming back
from one retreat to the next to the next
because on account of this wrong
approach they become dependent on that
calmness you know it's a good marketing
tool for just signing up for the next
one it's just that the people that
market it are victims themselves of the
same view yeah they're not doing it
delivered they're not doing it
deliberately yeah you